Robert F. Archibald PhD

DATA SCIENTIST · ASTROPHYSICIST

Montreal, QC

□ (514) 210-5775 | 🗷 archibald.rob@gmail.com | 💣 robertarchibald.ca | 🛅 robert-archibald-304512123

Summary _____

An astrophysicist by training, my background and training has been a demonstrable asset in my current role at Manulife as a Senior Data Scientist.

The skills, techniques and expertise gained in research have proven essential in the corporate/business setting helping draw out novel and actionable solutions from raw data.

I actively seek new problems and enjoy digging into data with the goal of transforming it into an accessible easily-understood narrative. Using statistics modeling to make the data tell a story is vital in anticipating where preparations may be needed and choosing the appropriate steps to take.

Work Experience _____

Manulife Montreal, QC

SENIOR DATA SCIENTIST

November 2019 - Present

• Reduced cost & compute time of stochastic market simulations by >90%, while satisfying the tight constraints of a heavily regulated industry.

Manulife / ICON Consulting

Toronto, Ont

HIGH PERFORMANCE COMPUTING SPECIALIST

September 2018 - November 2019

- Maintained python azure sdk tools to manage a large (~ 2000 vm) scalable compute environment for batch processing jobs.
- Developed a fully unit tested data validation / ETL tool that could parse & compare data from COBOL files, SQL, csvs, excel files, & more.
- CI-CD of python dash web apps to live monitor usage & costs.

University of Toronto Ont.

POSTDOCTORAL FELLOW

September 2017 - September 2018

 Designed & implemented an automatic search of X-ray telescope data (~similar to video) to flag interesting, time varying sources in a many year, 100s of Gb dataset.

McGill Montreal QC

RESEARCH ASSOCIATE, DOCTORAL WORK

May 2011 - August 2017

- Developed a python based software package to do near real-time analysis of on ongoing multi-year monitoring program of several objects
- Planned observing campaigns of many pulsars using space based telescopes to make efficient use of resources.
- Published 25 scientific articles with > 800 citations in peer reviewed journals.

Education

McGill Montreal, QC

PHD (Physics)

June 2014 - October 2017

• Thesis Title: X-ray Timing of Young Pulsars; Supervisor: Prof. V. M. Kaspi

• Thesis fille. A-ray filming of fourig ruisars, Supervisor. Froi. v. M. Naspi

Montreal, QC

MSc (Physics)

McGill

September 2011 - June 2014

• Thesis Title: An Anti-glitch in a Magnetar; Supervisor: Prof. V. M. Kaspi

Dalhousie University

Halifax, NS

BSc (Physics)

September 2007 - June 2011

• Thesis Title: Factoring by Adiabatic Quantum Computation; Supervisor: Prof. J. Kyriakidis

FEBRUARY 24, 2022 ROBERT F. ARCHIBALD · RÉSUMÉ